What's up folks, I'm gonna try something different today.
I'm gonna build an MCP server in five prompts.
I'm gonna make these prompts available to you
so you can follow along.
And we're hopefully gonna learn a little bit
of something about MCP servers,
but also how to do AI assisted development.
Because yeah, you've got vibe coding on one side,
and I like to think of there as AI assisted development
on the other, the serious stuff.
And it turns out that planning and documentation
and doing the boring stuff is really, really important
for this kind of sensible side of death.
We're starting off with an empty directory in cursor here.
And to start off, I'm just gonna paste in this prompt.
And while that's running, I'm just gonna show you
the structure of the prompt that we have here.
There are three main sections, we have a problem,
which is essentially a description of the problem
that this prompt is designed to solve.
We want to set up a new MCP server written in TypeScript,
we're starting from an empty directory.
We need to set up the basic file system,
install the dependencies, set up the project structure.
The supporting information is all the information
that the LLM needs to carry out the task.
In this case, I've added sections on the tools
that we want to use, for instance, PNPM,
and then also on the proposed file structure
that I would like to use here.
So it's stuff about the important files.mdc file,
package.json.tsconfig, sourcemain.ts,
Gitignore, et cetera.
And finally, the steps to complete are literally
the step-by-step things that the LLM should do
in order to complete the task.
You don't need to manually write this all out,
you can use it all to complete,
or you can prompt actually to get this structure out for you.
But I've found these three top level headings
to be really useful in just focusing
my writing and my prompting.
Okay, let's see what it put together.
We've got a TSconfig file,
which is basically ripped verbatim from the prompt.
We've got a PNPM lock file, which is nice,
so it knows that we're supposed to use PNPM.
We've got a package.json file with a bunch of stuff
that we're supposed to be in here.
In the prompt, I specify type module,
bin, I build and dev, and all the dependencies and stuff.
We've got our Gitignore with disk and node modules, very nice.
And we've got a source directory with a bunch of stuff
that we specified in the prompt.
This is ripped pretty much verbatim
from model context protocols SDK, read me.
And for now, it's using the standard IO server transport.
We can see that the LLM got stuck in a couple of places.
It can try to install the wrong version
of model context protocol SDK,
and then it was corrected by this big, beautiful error message,
very, very nice.
And actually that was the only place.
So it followed the step-by-step instructions really nice.
Let's head to prompt number two.
Our MCP server currently doesn't do anything.
Let's hook it up to GitHub so it can respond
to issues and pull requests.
We're going to use OctoKit for this, which is GitHub's SDK.
It's going to need to know about TSX and .n.
In the supporting information, I'm also telling it
to always declare tool descriptions.
Because when you call server.tool,
you can either pass in a name or pass in a name
and a description.
And the description is always nicer
because it means that the MCP client knows
what this tool actually does.
Then finally, in the steps to complete,
I'm giving it loads of functions that I want it to write.
Now in the app, let's open up a new chat
and paste this in.
So it's done a few things already.
It's added.nv to gitignore.
It's created a demo.n file for me, very nice.
And it's also updated the dev script
to use the .n file using n file from TSX.
I'm pretty sure that in the pre-training data,
it didn't know how to do this.
It doesn't know TSX that well.
And so I made sure I added that in the supporting information
and now it does it.
Now it's asking to install OctoKit, which is very nice.
I really like it when it uses PNPM to install OctoKit.
Because it means that it gets the latest version automatically
instead of just guessing the version
that was in its pre-training data.
Now it's creating this massive GitHub functions file.
It's done a really good job here.
I have barely included any information about OctoKit
in the supporting information or anything.
And it's just managing to cleanly, boop, boop, boop, slam out.
I assume this is because the GitHub REST API
has been around for a long time,
so it's probably in the training data somewhere.
It's also updated the important files.mdc
to add this GitHub file to it and getignore.n, very nice.
And finally, it's now added all of these different tools.
Here, get pull requests, create issue comments.
If I scan through these, we can see all of them,
create pull request comment.
And all of these like extra ZOD parameters
to make sure that the MCP client can call it correctly.
Again, we're really leaning on the model's
inbuilt knowledge of the GitHub API here.
We can see that these very simple descriptions here
led to an extremely complex, well actually,
not that complex implementation,
but like this small amount of words
led to a lot of code, very cool.
Now, before we get this running,
I actually want to, instead of using standard IO,
I want to use prompt three to convert it to SSE instead.
I'm on WSL and I've not been able to get cursor working
with MCP servers using standard IO on WSL.
It's quite complicated.
In the supporting information,
I've got a few battle scars kind of recorded here.
I've only been able to get this to work using
the express framework.
I tried getting it to work with Hono,
but wasn't able to.
And I've added here the example implementation
that I've got in an article on AI here.
The steps to complete are pretty simple here.
So let's open up a new chat with nothing
in the context, bugging in and get it going.
So it knows to install Express very nice
and by doing it by PNPM,
it's installing the latest versions.
So as expected, it's done a really good job,
basically copy and pasting the code
that was in the supporting information
down into this express area here.
It's done something slightly odd in the package.json,
which has added this actual start script here.
Not sure why it's done that.
I didn't tell it to do that.
I suppose it's useful in some sense,
but we're going to be using the dev script here
so we don't really need this start one.
In fact, I'm just going to delete it.
Off screen, I've just gone away,
grabbed a GitHub personal access token
with the right scopes,
and I've added it to my.m file.
So I should now be able to run PNPM run dev
and the server is running on port 8080.
In my cursor setup, I have it pointed to
localhost 8080, SSE.
I was getting an error here saying client closed, okay?
It turns out that deleting this line,
app.usexpress.json,
going back to cursor settings, refreshing,
and now everything is working.
So now that cursor is hooked up to my MCP server,
we can say, tell me about the open PRs
on MacBook everlights, which is one of the reposite.
It's telling me to call an MCP tool,
list pull requests, okay?
Sounds great.
We can go into here and actually see
what was returned from this.
So we've got the result inside here.
Big loaded data from the GitHub API.
There is probably too much data here.
I would probably go in and kill some of this
because if we plow all of this data into our LM,
we're gonna run out of context window pretty quickly.
But in this case, it was able to summarize it for us.
So we've got PR 114, fixed chart colors by dog poor hat.
I will get to this PR, I promise.
I've just got a lot on an added failing test
for the AI SDK image traces by, oh, that's me, okay?
Created by the repository owner, 31st, 2024.
Cool.
All this to say, we've hooked up our MCP server
to our MCP client and can now start doing stuff with it.
Let's dive back into our code base
and start looking at a couple of refactors
that I think I want to make.
Yeah, this is invite coding where we don't care at all
about the code.
We actually do care about the code
because the code is the input to our LLM.
And funnily enough, things like file structures and things,
things I've never actually really cared about as a proper dev.
They're kind of useful tools to be able to communicate
the LLM quickly, what a file is for.
If our file structure is confusing or too diffuse or strange,
then it's going to kind of trick the LLM into doing
weird, weird things.
And currently we have one enormous like main.ts file,
which is I think doing a bit too much.
We kind of, it's declaring the server transport.
It's declaring the server initially.
It's adding all of these tools onto here.
It's just doing too much and it means
that the LLM might end up doing things
like adding a random tools file
and then not bringing it back to this.
So in this prompt, we are breaking up the large files
into smaller chunks.
Each file may contain multiple GitHub actions or tools,
but they should be split by domain
and ensure that all major files are added
to the important files.mdc file.
Again, just keeping that up to date.
Let's start a new chat, paste this in, and off we go.
Okay, our refactor is complete
and we now have a new file structure.
We now have source, GitHub,
with a bunch of functions and tools underneath it.
We also have a server, I suppose,
with the app and the transport.
And finally, we have main.ts,
which basically just has an MCP server,
then says register GitHub tools,
create the express app and tell it to listen.
The GitHub functions look pretty similar
to what they had before.
It's just split up into different files.
So we've got issues and poor requests currently.
We do have a barrel file here,
which show in libraries I don't love,
but is fine for this, I suppose.
But crucially, our important file stuff here
has all been added.
You can see how the file structure has an impact
on the way that the LLM understands your code base.
If I was extending this out to a massive, massive code base,
I would probably not have all of the individual issues
and pull stuff here,
because GitHub would know the function of the folder.
And the folder would essentially be the way
that it could then discover all of the information
within that feature.
This also means you can have cursor rules
attached to different folders as well.
For instance, this one is auto-attached
where we could say,
oh, let's say it only matters on source, GitHub, for instance,
and on all files in there.
But since this one is properly global,
let's just have it always attached to every conversation.
So now our refactor step is complete.
Let's actually add a new feature here
to test out all the infrastructure that we've now built.
I want to be able to check the status of actions
on the MCP server.
In other words, check out workflows
in GitHub using my cool thing.
Let's bung this in again with no context needed
and just let it work.
We can see by the way that the way cursor index is stuff here,
we have listed items in GitHub source functions.
So it's actually looking in the folder for the files.
And it can see pretty clearly that it just needs
to add a new domain into here
and add actions.ts into GitHub functions.
Okay, it's now finished and we can see
that we've actually become the victim
of our very first weird, weird screw up.
First of all, the LLM appears to have hallucinated
the idea that there is a create tool function
somewhere in the repo.
So it's completely just lost the plot
and imagined this create tool.js file.
It's then used that invented its own API here
in order to create these list workflow runs tool.
So I'm actually going to rerun this
and edit the steps to complete.
The issue here is that the LLM didn't go and look for
the existing implementations to copy them.
This is a context window problem.
It didn't have the right stuff in the context window
in order to be able to go and find the right solution.
I could take the existing implementation
and put it in the supporting information
but I think it's just cleaner to tell it to go
and look at the existing implementation first.
So I've now told it in the start of the steps to complete,
look at the existing implementations of functions
and tools in the correct directory,
load them into your context window, be very specific.
So let's take this entire prompt
and stick it in the chat window.
We're actually going to use this chat here.
We're going to go all the way up to the top
and we're essentially just going to paste it in here instead.
So we're going to override the previous chat message
and then just go back.
This means that all of the code that we had before
essentially gets removed.
So we don't no longer have that dodgy action stuff.
You can see it's all been removed
if I move my face.
Ooh, I just go over here for a sec.
All the action stuff has been removed
from functions and tools.
We can see now that thanks to our explicit instruction,
it's going first, let's look at the existing
GitHub functions and tools.
Let me check the implementation
of one of the existing function files.
Let me check how these things are exposed to tools.
It's reading the correct files,
loading them into its context window.
Okay, we now have an actions file
that looks very much like the other actions that we had here.
Again, it's relying on its training data,
really spitting out these OctoKit functions.
And here we can see the actions are much more like it.
Just like this issues file here
where we have registered issues tools,
we have an actions thing here
that says register action tools.
And so the previous hallucination,
I mean, was that our fault?
Was it the LLM's fault?
Maybe the LLM should have been smart enough
to understand that it should have looked
in those files first.
But honestly, I put this down to me
not thinking ahead, not understanding
what the LLM's context was supposed to be.
It had to have those files in context.
If it didn't have the files in context,
it had no idea what it was going to do.
So explicitly telling it,
load those files into context
and essentially copy them is the way to go.
So there we go, in a series of five prompts,
we have a bunch of stuff that can look like an MCP server.
We have a bunch of folders
that will allow us to add features here
where the LLM understands what it's supposed to do.
We have all the infrastructure needed
to run this as an MCP server locally.
And we've done this with prompts
that use a three section heading kind of thing.
They explain the problem that we're supposed to be solving.
They give the LLM any supporting information it needs,
like external resources.
And then you have the explicit steps to complete,
which is really important.
I hope you enjoyed this.
I definitely enjoyed making this
and I'll be back with more.
See you very soon.